Lacona, IA 50139 Cell: 515-249-6638

Email: putz.austin@gmail.com

# **AUSTIN PUTZ**

## Curriculum Vitae

#### PERSONAL SUMMARY

Austin grew up on a diversified family farm where he helped manage 600 acres that included row crops, cattle, horses, and pigs among others species. As an undergraduate student at Iowa State University he worked in several molecular genetic labs to gain an understanding of molecular biology before moving to quantitative genetics. Internships with Fast Genetics and Smithfield Premium Genetics have been valuable as a future professional in the field. At North Carolina State University he has focused on learning numerous technical skills (e.g. R, Unix/Linux, SAS, Python, and LaTeX) along with basic quantitative genetics and animal breeding. He has already completed five graduate level statistics courses that have given him an advantage in data analysis. His goal is to complete his Master's degree in the Spring of 2015 and begin his PhD in the Fall of 2015 after completing another internship next summer.

## **EDUCATION**

Doctor of Philosophy

Iowa State University

2018 (expected)
Ames, IA

Major: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Minor: Statistics

Master of ScienceJuly 2015North Carolina State UniversityRaleigh, NC

Major: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Minor: Statistics

GPA: 4.0

Bachelor of ScienceMay 2013Iowa State UniversityAmes, IA

Major: Animal Science Summa Cum Lauda

GPA: 3.93

COMPUTER SKILLS Advanced: R, Unix/Linux

Intermediate: LaTeX, SAS, BLUPF90 Programs

Beginner: Python, DMU Programs

# WORK EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

**Iowa State University** 

Aug 2015 - Present

Ames, IA

Started my PhD under Jack Dekkers. I'll be researching disease resistance.

Genetics data analyst

May 2015 – August 2015

The Maschhoffs

Carlyle, IL

Worked on two projects with The Maschhoffs. The first was analyzing conformation traits scored at off-test. The second was to calculate a weaned pig value across farms.

Graduate Research Assistant

Aug 2013 – July 2015

**North Carolina State University** 

Raleigh, NC

Master's degree started in the fall of 2013 working with Smithfield Premium Genetics data. Worked on a new trait, litter size at day 5, for their maternal line indexes.

Research and Development Intern

Summer 2013/2014

**Smithfield Premium Genetics** 

Rose Hill, NC

Full-time intern summer 2013. Part-time summer 2014.

- Data management
- Variance component estimation
- ◆ GWAS
- Accuracy comparison
- Collected carcass traits in packing plant
- Assisted in data collection for growth curve study
- Final presentation

Research Assistant

Aug 2012 – May 2013

## **Swine Molecular Genetics Lab**

Ames. IA

Worked for Dr. Chris Tuggle on 2 projects. 1) Prepared RNA samples for subsequent RNA-Seq analysis on the residual feed intake grant and 2) assisted in the development of allelespecific PCR procedures to genotype SNPs associated with PRRS.

- DNA/RNA isolation
- Created cDNA
- ◆ PCR and qPCR
- NanoDrop for concentrations
- Bioanalyzer for RNA quality

Breeding and Farrowing Technician

May 2012 – Aug 2012

**Fast Genetics** 

Cando, ND

6,000-head sow multiplying unit in North Dakota. Half the summer was spent as a breeding technician and the second half was spent in farrowing.

- Artificially inseminated main line sows and gilts
- Gave shots
- Daily feeding and observation
- Managed data
- Induced sows and gilts
- Delivered piglets

#### Lab Assistant

Jan 2012 – May 2012

## **Beef Molecular Genetics Lab**

Ames, IA

Worked for Dr. James Reecy as a lab assistant.

- Data collection on farm and in packing plants
- Basic data management
- NanoDrop
- Basic lab chores

### Lab Assistant

May 2011 – Dec 2011

Ames, IA

#### Soils Microbiology Lab

- Micro-balanced
- Sampled soil and gas
- Processed soil
- Ran enzyme analyses
- Managed data
- Basic lab chores

### Barn Crew Member

Aug 2010 – May 2011

## **Iowa State University Veterinary School**

Ames, IA

- Strict biosecurity
  - Maintained horse wards, bovine, ICU, and isolation
  - Disinfected stalls after animal departure
  - Regular maintenance of stalls

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Jan 2014 – April 2014

Raleigh, NC

Teaching assistant for the undergraduate reproductive physiology class under Dr. Whisnant.

• Set up labs

North Carolina State University

- Assisted in teaching
- Lectured genetic improvement lab
- Checked weekly assignments and quizzes

Organic Chemistry Tutor

Jan 2012 – May 2012

## **Iowa State University**

Ames, IA

Tutored two students in Chem 331.

• Reviewed class notes

- Solved review problems together
- Helped review for exams

#### REFEREED JOURNALS

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer. 2014. Variance component estimates for alternative litter size and piglet mortality traits in swine. J. Anim. Sci. In preparation.

#### **ABSTRACTS**

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, M. T. Knauer. Variance component estimates for alternative litter size and piglet mortality traits. 2014. Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

#### **PROJECTS**

## man pages for BLUPF90 programs

Developed Unix/Linux based man (manual) pages for the BLUPF90 family of programs. This allows new and old users a way of accessing documentation from within a terminal window. Additional information was added for things not documented precisely by the UGA group.

## vim syntax highlighting for BLUPF90 programs

Created a basic syntax-highlighting file for use with the BLUPF90 family of programs. This will allow users to easily identify mistakes that could be extremely detrimental to running variance components or genomic analyses.

#### **HONORS**

Lane Wells Scholarship	August 2011
Iowa State University	Ames, IA

Kenneth and Ruth Wagner Scholarship August 2012

Iowa State University Ames, IA

Arthur Molln Scholarship August 2012

Iowa State University Ames, IA

National Pork Board Scholarship April 2013
National Pork Board Clive, IA

\$3,500 as the second ranked applicant in the 2013 pool.

#### **SHORT COURSES**

Programming and computer algorithms in animal breeding with focus on genomic selection and single-step GBLUP

University of Georgia May 2014

#### REFERENCES

#### Dr. Mark Knauer

North Carolina State University Assistant Professor Master's Committee Chair Phone: 919-515-8797

Email: mtknauer@ncsu.edu

## Dr. Kent Gray

Smithfield Premium Genetics

Director of Research and Development

Master's Committee Member

Phone: 910-282-4227

Email: kent.gray@spgenetics.com

# **Dr. Chris Tuggle**

Iowa State University

Professor

Phone: 515-294-4252

Email: cktuggle@iastate.edu

## Dr. Tom Baas

Iowa State University

Professor

Phone: 515-294-6728

Email: tjbaas@iastate.edu